Russell Dias

Tech Founder | Senior Product Manager | Solutions Architect | Engineering

L +91 9741898149

Russell Dias

Q Lisbon, Portugal

Senior product and engineering professional with 6+ years of experience. Currently, I'm a full-stack engineering lead at YLabs, heading serverless efforts and optimizing cloud infrastructure costs. I'm also a serial tech founder with three scalable startups, including Fluxforms (an AI-based forms analytics tool), Parentheses Labs (a software consultancy), and Blip Chat (an AI-powered virtual assistant). Previously, I've also worked on product strategy, launches, and development for leading med tech, ed tech, SaaS, and U.S. government organizations (including Conwaste, Thena, Archimydes, Taloflow, and QuantLegal Tech).



Check out my website for my work portfolio: russdias.com

Skills

- Product management
- · AWS serverless architecture
- Artificial intelligence
- · Problem solving

- React and NextJS expertise
- Product lifecycle management
- · Sales and negotiation
- Full stack engineering

Work Experience

Ylabs (CyberRwanda - a digital platform for sex education)

Oct 2022 - Present

- Drastically reduced cloud infrastructure costs from \$500/m to just \$5/m by migrating to a serverless setup.
- Migrated from a legacy codebase to a more efficient NextJS system within 2 months.
- Implemented USSD in 10 days for the app's eCommerce page.
- Optimized app experiences by moving to the latest React Native version, leading to a 3x faster experience for end users.
- Implemented a pub-sub architecture to help with async tasks and reduce wait time for app users.
- Contributed to a study on <u>Sustainable and Scalable Features in Digital Health</u> by the University of San Francisco.

Fluxforms (AI-based forms analytics tool)

March 2022 - Present

- Designed and developed an Al-based forms analytics app within 33 days.
- Scaled to 5000+ users in 2 months.
- Migrated to serverless architecture and optimized tech costs by 95%.
- Led VC and Angel investor pitches and landed an initial seed round of \$150K.
- Managed a remote team of 4 engineers.

Parentheses Labs (Software consultancy)

May 2022 - Present

- Co-founded a software consultancy and scaled to a remote team of 4 designers and 8 engineers within 8 months.
- Successfully built 10+ software products for clients in the U.S. and U.K.
- Scaled net revenue by 1.5x within our first year in operation.
- Led sales prospecting efforts and business development calls.
- Built all the products using the AWS serverless infrastructure.

- Used GPT 4 and vector embeddings to build a chat-based support assistant within 9 days.
- Successfully tested the beta version with a closed group of 4 large-scale companies, reducing workloads by up to 80% for customer support teams.
- Built the entire infrastructure on AWS serverless using SAM, effectively keeping costs as low as \$10/mo.

Taloflow - YCombinator (Cloud vendor evaluation tool)

July 2022 - Feb 2023

- Built a collaborative notion like editor for cloud cost estimations using NextJS and Slate.
- Through research and feedback, optimized the interface leading to a 2x increase in editor performance.
- Managed a team of 3 engineers remotely.

Thena (A customer engagement platform for Slack)

Jan 2023 - Jul 2023

- Built the MVP that led to a \$2M funding round.
- Built and optimized a cost-efficient cloud infrastructure for scale.
- Set code and infra standards for the team to build faster.
- Cleaned up the backend pipeline to ensure snappy responses based on user feedback.
- Implemented a pub-sub architecture to aid async tasks and reduce wait time.

Conwaste (A NYC 311 service for San Juan, Puerto Rico)

Jan 2021 - Dec 2022

- Developed and managed 2 mobile apps and dashboards for the U.S. government and stakeholders.
- Developed the entire infrastructure using infrastructure as code.
- Built CI/CD pipelines to help ensure smooth delivery for releases.
- Led a remote team of 6 engineers.
- Liaised between the stakeholders, QA team, clients, and officials.

Archimydes (SF-based software consultancy)

Jan 2020 - Dec 2022

- Worked as a solution architect for multiple projects handling infrastructure.
- Worked as an engineering lead doing code reviews, customer onboarding, and client requirement checks.
- Built internal app templates for scalability, security, and performance.
- Performed software security audits for clients.

QuantLegal Tech (VC facilitator application)

2017 - 2020

- Worked with the frontend team to build the admin apps and dashboards
- Migrated a legacy create-react-app JavaScript codebase to a NextJS Typescript app.
- Built server-side rendered dashboards for the app.
- Built a scalable and extensible design system

Experience with Software Engineering

- NextJS
- TypeScript/JavaScript
- AWS Cloudformation
- React/Server Components
- AWS serverless services

- JIRA
- GCP serverless services
- SQL, NoSQL, caching & vector databases
- Cloud architecture
- Go Lang

Education

Bachelors of Visual Communication

St. Joseph's University